you want
meditate watch your
bread
e
e e
you come to the golden
room like liquid gold okay spread all
over the objects of the
room e
see the sky blue sky endless Blue
Sky
e e
look at the mountains Valley between you
and the
mountain e
ask your teacher to
come sit with
you e
then just focus on their presence in the
room
try to cut through to this feeling
of happiness or
satisfaction or peace that they're
there
then that will take you to
n and you skip the agitation and
dullness
to kind of contentment or peace that
they're
there a feeling that you don't need to
do anything else or go anywhere else or
think of anything else try to go
straight try to go straight to the
n e
come back to
the sense of contentment and well-being
in their presence
there's no place else you'd rather
be
e e
slowly come back to this
room then open your eyes on
your all right
uh there's a question here from last
night it's kind of sneaky but let's just
knock it out
uh if you're looking at the
pen and you're seeing it as a you know
we call reasonably as a pen what's the
Sans you can't say anything Sanskrit
word for reasonably is Perman okay so
you know
correctly or we should rather say
reasonably uh you are seeing a
pen and
then uh if you're not in IR
higher your your some part of your
perception is infected by seeing that as
though the peness were coming from the
pen
okay the penis is really coming from you
okay then the question that the person
asked was how can you how can you be
having two perceptions at the same time
what's the classical answer to all such
questions yeah the toggle the toggle
thing okay so the mind is
having 65 mini perceptions per per
second and it's toggling between the the
two and it's correct that you can't have
you can't really be having two
perceptions at the same millisecond it's
not possible so they're not technically
mixed like water and milk AR they that
was their point okay all
right uh get out your posters and try to
crumple as much as you can
everybody who intends to pass on this
lineage should have a poster open in
front of them and be making notes okay
if you were at Sarah and get you through
Terin and sees you without an open
notebook you get a rosary on the
him he even checks to see what you
wrote so we're going to review let's
talk about the level we've gone through
so far uh Sam Joka was you can't say
anything anyway Sam jok is where the
mind you're supposed to pretend that
you're saying oh the mind you're just
starting on your meditation
okay and that's achieved
through uh to he went like that uh
learning okay hearing about how to
meditate from your teacher okay uh then
we
have uh
number uh Gund jopa oh this was fly on
the cpai right then Gund jopa is the fly
is having a conversation on the
cowpie okay and some continuity
okay uh number three was uh
lenda which means patches
of distraction right off the object as
opposed to patches on the object so when
they call it patch like meditation I I
think it's a
problem that was
13 and now we could go over to
16 which is called n
Joka uh B describes it as the mind is
tightly on the object
okay and from number six this number 16
from this point on you can cannot lose
the object
okay but you can still have very
noticeable dullness and agitation okay
at
16 if you use learning to get to the
first one what do you learn what do you
use to get to the second one it would be
uh she went like that s which means uh
you start to think about what your
teacher said to you at home okay
s and then the first two levels are
achieved through some kind of very
conscious effort okay it has to be you
know you have to sit down and crank your
mind down get it quiet takes like a few
minutes you just fight to even get there
okay in the first two as we said the
staying on the object is is less than
the off the object
okay and number
three uh we're more time on the object
than off the
object and uh during the first
four you are developing your uh TBA okay
TBA means the ability to bring the
object back which is the chain in the
Monk's uh left hand okay the chain in
the left hand of the mon was the ability
to bring yourself back to the object
quickly and by the fourth stage that
that capacity is developed fully they
say it's like a a full grown person as a
like here at this point your ability to
bring your mind back is like a child and
here it's like a teenager and then here
it's like a by by level four your
ability to bring it back is like a
full-grown adult okay
the elephant was your
mind what color was dness right the
monkey was your the monkey was losing
was flying off the object uh not losing
but but flying off the
object and the Blackness represented uh
agitation or going off to desirable
object so the mon all the monkey is all
kinds of going off the Blackness was to
a desirable
object then the Y
no and then Shin Shin you have to
develop okay Shin is uh we call it
watchfulness or guard M or something
like that and uh I think by today you
should we should be in our meditations
we should be thinking about Shin Shin
means uh the alarm mine that goes off
and says we're off the object okay or or
things are getting dull in here you know
or you're starting to think about ice
cream something like that so we have to
today I would suggest that during our
meditations you try to try to get in
touch with your shashan okay uh we all
have a Shan naturally everybody has one
I
mean sooner or later you notice that the
pot is boiling over boiling on the stove
and stuff is pouring out
and remember CH used to call me Po
burner that was my second like what my
fifth name uh but I can't tell you some
of them but uh pot burner meant I I just
would be reading a book or something and
I was supposed to be the cook but I was
like the worst cook and it would the
thing would just be boiling over and
burning and and I'd be reading a book
and uh that's no shashan okay shashan
should have detected that the you know
that the water was getting near the top
of the pot and and then done something
about it okay okay so I think we're
ready to go to number five let's see if
there's anything between
there how about
17 17 I think he's on I think he's on
the flame
okay I think he's referring to the flame
but that happened to represent a very
strong uh developed sh so we're on the
right track okay so 17 is a very
strongly that flame is a strongly
developed capacity to catch yourself
when you're wandering or getting dull or
getting agitated okay
then the
uh they say uh
agitation is losing its power okay the
monkey's head is becoming white
right going off to other objects that
you enjoy thinking about your plans for
the
future
uh right below the number 18 the
monkey's head is getting a little bit
[Music]
white sorry uh a rabbit yeah no the
rabbit what was the rabbit is
that settled dness yeah no so I'm talk I
am talking about the monkey his head is
getting a little bit white which means
the
agitation is getting better then we get
up to uh
number
19 uh number 19 above you can see a
monkey grabbing uh a fruit okay do you
see
him he's to the left of of number 19 on
the
chart he's in the he's up in the fruit
tree there you see
him anybody doesn't see
him he's uh the the text says he's he's
reaching for a second fruit which means
uh a special kind of distraction where
you are thinking about a virtuous
subject see so the that guy grabbing for
a fruit is a special kind of
distraction gei
Michael's next project
it okay and and in other circumstances
that might be a a good thing to do to
think of one more virtuous project but
in during a meditation it's a bad thing
to do okay I don't know if it's a bad
karma I guess it would be a bad karma I
don't know but
uh but
anyway around this time you're supposed
to be aware that you shouldn't do that
and that there are other kinds of
distraction than thinking about lunch or
thinking about the person who bugs you
okay so that's a third kind of
distruction section
uh the cheex says watchfulness will not
let the Mind get distracted and
uplifting your heart leads you to a
state of one-pointed
concentration uh so we have to talk
about uplifting okay uplifting heart say
sing you can't
say you should cancel that no doing
class
no it would be a virtuous
dist uh anyway
s means uh I learned the word because uh
I told people recently uh when I got to
the
monastery I wanted to I had learned some
Tibetan and I I wanted to learn to speak
well and then ruche had another student
art angle who was already speaking
extremely fluently so of course I was
jealous and uh then I got there and I'm
like okay R you have to teach
me you have to teach me you know to B I
want to talk like art you know and then
he said no no you're not going to learn
to Buton uh you have to speak English
and then I got more jealous uh and then
uh he said I have to learn English so
you're going to be my English teacher so
you're not allowed to speak to V in the
house so I'm okay then uh when we used
to have breakfast together the three of
us uh I subscribed to a Tibetan
newspaper and I just ignored them and I
just read the newspaper to learn how to
speak uh in my head you know so
anyway s TI I read in the newspaper was
uh where somebody got an award
wward okay
uh like like uh the president gave some
award to somebody that was calleda okay
that's how I learned the word then in in
meditation it means uh the Tupa part
means to praise right like it means to
praise somebody and give them an award
so s means you praise yourself okay you
think of good things about yourself and
your life okay so when your mind is
feeling down when the level of the mind
is
down uh when you feel some kind of
dullness in the mind then sopa means
uplift your mind okay with uh we talked
about it you can say I'm one in a
million person who made it here uh I
must have some good karma if I'm here at
Friendly Pines freezing my ARs and uh
you know you should think that you're a
lucky person you know and uh sometimes
here you can do a thankful thankfulness
meditation okay that's a very very
powerful meditation for uplifting your
mind so
you you just start making a list of all
the people in your life that you would
like to think okay and then that once
you start that list will proliferate
okay you can't uh you can't come to the
end of all the people that you need to
think in your life you would never
finish the list okay and it's an
extremely uh
Pleasant meditation so you just uh go
through it's called a Shon right it's a
list meditation and you just go through
and you you think of all the people you
have to think in your life and at the
beginning you're it's a Stutter Steps
you're like uh let me think and then
later as you do it more and more they're
they're just pile up people pile up the
trick is that you cannot be thankful to
someone for
anything unless it's something good
about yourself you see you if you think
about it you see if you say I thank my
high school teachers it's because you're
happy about what they gave you you
wouldn't thank the teacher who didn't
teach you anything right so the process
of thanking
or you're recognizing something good
about yourself you know you you
thank I don't know you thank your
parents for giving you life but you
can't do that without thinking your life
is somehow precious so the the the
exercise of thanking other people
uplifts the mind and it's a self- award
thing s okay so uh they're
[Music]
talking where was
he at level uh 20 at number
20 uh we are using S more
and the Monk Is Now actively using see
down here well he's got he's got the
Gema he's pulling back the object quite
strongly the the recollection or the
ability to bring the object back was
already well
develop at at between 20 and 21 and
what's he doing with his right hand oh
you can't
answer his sh is really hooked in you
know his watchfulness of his mind is
really
start which brings us to uh
21 which is called
d uh those of you who know Tibetan or
some Tibetan dula means Vana okay d
means
via dwa
means to tame a wild thing okay so like
when you tame a
horse when you break a horse it's called
daa okay a wild
horse and the Tibetan word for a
disciple or or a spiritual student is
dja the thing which is to be
broken all right d and then uh the
monks the or the order of monks and nuns
their their their code is called
D the the breaking code for breaking
your own Pride breaking your own
ignorance breaking
your bad habits okay so anyway they've
chosen that word for number 21 which is
meditation level number five okay and
it's called we translated it there as
controlling the mind okay controlling
the
m i want you to uh will we'll make a
list of what's going on at that point
and then we'll we'll do another brief
meditation
okay at this point they say the mind is
overly concentrated within okay so the
process of
meditation is the process of focusing
the mind inside right so it's prara
right normally the mind
is radiating out from the the core and
and thinking and projecting
and and perceiving right and then the
process of meditation is to turn the
Mind
within and bring it inside for example
uh in yoga prara means
that it's one of the asanga right what
is it
Yama body okay so it's prara means the
ability to bring the mind in Focus the
mind in we normally do it automatically
during sleep okay uh there's a natural
prara going on during sleep and the mind
is is uh withdrawn from the world so
prar means withdraw the senses from the
world and bring the mind in okay that's
called n dupa the mind at number 21 you
are overdoing it okay at number 21
you're overdoing bringing the Mind into
their mind
okay which triggers chingao which is
what uh D subtle dullness okay so
overdoing it triggers subtle dullness
what would be the fix for that that's
where they mention s okay that's
uplifting the Mind
somehow but what did we just do during
our
meditation to cut over to cut over
dullness and agitation we went straight
to L okay we went straight to the
enjoyment Factor you know like trying to
take some pleasure or contentment in the
object so you can do that
okay if the mind is overly concentrated
and you're feeling in they call it Kudo
Kudo means
uh the feeling you get when you walk
down an alley which is too
narrow okay like I was in Morocco in
marash and you know we were thinking
maybe we'd get kidnapped if we weren't
careful and then we were going down
these kopo
alleys you know and then you feel a
little bit
you know you feel vulnerable in a in a
way
of you're all closed in you can't get
anywhere you can't escape if you had to
escape that's Kudo so uh to release that
or to to let go of that uh you can go
straight to the pleasurable feeling or
some kind of try to think about's
contentment okay like you're willing to
sit there because you're enjoying what's
going on and you you don't have any
what do you go you're not fidgeting
right the fidgeting goes away because
you're having a good time and you're
enjoying what's going on okay so combat
fidgeting with
uh some kind of feeling of contentment
or well-being okay and that then you go
straight to okay and that will release
the K of the mind that will release the
narrow Alleyway feeling of the mind okay
and you'll feel more expensive there's a
big big thing in meditation of trying to
feel more more expensive that's why
we're doing the sky and the valley and
all that
okay we'll have to do an exercise before
we finish the week and maybe you can
work on it at home okay but classically
when they teach the nine levels to a
student they'll say they'll quiz the
student and they'll say what
distinguishes number two from number one
what's the difference what has changed
between number two and number one what
has changed between number three and
number two okay so I'll give that to you
as an assignment okay like try to think
try to be able to answer quickly you
know what has what's the difference
between for example the difference
between number two and number one is
that you're still off the object most of
the time but less
often okay so I gave you the first
one and then you're going to have to go
through all the other ones
uh in this this case I'll just give you
the one for for number five and then
we'll do some meditation but what
differentiates number five from number
four is that there is no longer any
great
side there's no longer any gross
dullness or agitation okay the elephant
is half
white the monkey is mostly White
even the rabbit is half white okay so no
no no gross uh agitation or dullness
after that
okay he said Gross right which is why
there's still some black on those
CR okay let's do some
meditation I don't know if you noticed
but we're up to 10 or 15 minutes of high
quality and you didn't notice that the
time increased
okay watch your
breath there's nothing in the world
except your
breath
e e
come to the golden room
try to jump to that enjoyment of the
color of the room in the the feeling the
warm feeling in the color of the
room if you have enjoyment you won't be
distracted you won't feel
dull e
look out the window at the sky blue sky
expansive Blue
Sky
e
e e
look at the mountains B
then come back to the golden room and
ask your teacher to please sit in front
of you
feel their eyes on your eyes and feel
the love between you in the in the
Gaze stay on their eyes
try to get in touch with your sh try to
get in touch with the corner of your
mind which is watching whether the scene
is getting
dull or whether you're thinking about
lunch or even subtle agitation which
means the feeling of being about to
think about
lunch e
try to get in touch with your s
s's just detecting whether the
something's going wrong
try now to observe the difference
between Shin and DBA your watchfulness
which is detecting that something has
gone
wrong and then your Juma or the capacity
to pull yourself back to the object try
to actually observe those two working in
your own mind the detecting that the
mind has left the object and then the
conscious effort to bring the Mind back
to the object see if you can distinguish
between those two states of Mind within
your own
mind they are almost instantaneous it
takes a lot of observation to to locate
them to observe
them e
now see if you can isolate the mental
state of n see if you can
isolate a sense of contentment or
enjoyment on the
object get to know these three friends
watchfulness pulling the Mind
back and a deep sense of contentment
that would allow you to just stay
there e
okay good job feels really good come
back to this
room and
relax it feels really really good in the
room like I haven't had a room like that
for minut many years I
think I think you're doing really well
so uh keep it up okay I think the
silence helps but I think
you're I think you're getting into
this groove of of being able to observe
your own mind the subtle moving of your
own mind you know while you're in
meditation
so in meditation is this thing of
of a lot of people never observe their
own mind during medit
and then you you you want to get to
where you can isolate those three guys
oh there there went my sh you know my
watchfulness just went off and then oh I
think the Demba is the fastest one
hopefully but it
just the Shan says oh we're off the
object and then and then suddenly you're
on the object so try to catch the
interim try to catch the mind uh going
between the two uh detecting that the
mind is off and coming back cuz it's so
fast coming back that you can miss it
all right so try to detect the part of
the mind that detects that you're off
try to detect the part of mind that
pulls you back and then I think it's a
pleasure to to isolate the feeling of
contentment or satisfaction and and I I
really encourage you to work on that one
okay cuz that that's Nar right that
brings uh intensity on the object and
it's so easy um it's such a pleasant
place to be and then it it it cuts
through the the struggles not to be dull
or or agitated it just cuts through them
like there's no there's no struggle with
dullness and agitation you don't start
feeling sleepy and you don't start
thinking about lunch because you're just
having a good time where you are so try
to get in touch with the good time where
you are State of Mind okay and then I
think your meditation will get really
really powerful and I think you've seen
or you felt when you get home it'll be
better to start with tiny little
meditation five five six seven minutes
and then
slowly with the Nar it will just get
longer uh without struggleing you know
you won't have to say oh I I have to
stay for 23 minutes today or something
like that you will you will come out of
it and the clock will be over there and
you're like you know you think you're
seeing it wrong and and like a half hour
has passed and and you weren't aware of
anything it should be like that it
shouldn't be that you you get home and
you say I'm going to be a great meditor
I'm going to start with an hour and then
you're just struggling and your knees
are hurting and you're thinking about a
thousand different things and you're not
happy at all and you feel OB what you
okay
obligatory you feel like oh llamas told
me I had to meditate I I have to do it
uh it's not very fun you know like that
okay do it this way small
periods uh it go straight to the Nar
which means pick an object at the
beginning that you like okay that you
would like to hang out with
okay okay we'll stop there